Robert D. Eddy Papers MS168
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Robert D. Eddy Papers
1963 -- 1976
1935 -- 1982
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Eddy Sr., Robert Devereux
MS168
1.7 Linear Feet 2 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Personal papers; and Professional activities.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, publications, manuscripts, television scripts, lectures, notebooks and course materials, mostly dating from the 1960s and 1970s and relating to Eddy's professional and educational activities both at Tufts and elsewhere. Included are biographical material, lectures and writings related to Eddy's involvement in various professional associations, including the New England Association of Chemistry Teachers (NEACT) and the American Chemical Society (ACS), chemistry 'activities' (problem sets) designed by Eddy for Florida State University's Individualized Science Instruction System (ISIS) instruction manual (1975-1976), scripts from his WGBH televised chemistry courses for the U.S. Navy's Polaris University (1963), and papers concerning the development of the Tested Overhead Projection Series (TOPS) for classroom use (1965-1975).
Biographical / Historical
Robert Devereux Eddy Sr. (1914-1983) was a professor of chemistry at Tufts University from 1942-1976. Eddy was born in Providence, Rhode Island, on October 15, 1914. He received his A.B. from Brown University in 1935, his Master's degree from Princeton in 1938, and his PhD from the same institution the following year.
In 1939, Eddy began teaching at Tufts as an instructor; he was an assistant professor from 1942-1949, associate professor from 1949-1953, and full professor from 1953 until his retirement in 1976. In 1980 he was named professor emeritus.
Eddy is notable for his contributions to chemistry curriculum reform, at both high school and college levels. Around 1960 he took a two-year leave of absence from Tufts University to work with the Chemical Bond Approach Committee (CBA) on teaching aids and a laboratory manual for high school chemistry. CBA was a project sponsored by the National Science Foundation (NSF) geared towards improving high school chemistry education in the post-Sputnik era. In 1963 Eddy prepared 60 half-hour films on college chemistry for Harvard's Department of University Extension, for use at Polaris University, a project of the U.S. Navy. These films were prepared at the studios of WGBH, and students in the Boston area and on Polaris submarines took the courses for credit using the films. In 1965 Eddy took sabbatical leave to work as a visiting fellow at Princeton University, developing the Chemistry Lecture Demonstration using the Tested Overhead Projection Series (TOPS), which projected chemical reactions by overhead projector. In 1966 he traveled to Paris, France, to serve as honorary consultant to the Division of Science Teaching at the Department of Advancement of Science at UNESCO. At the time, the goal of the Division of Science Teaching was to strengthen UNESCO's program for teaching basic science at pre-university level in Latin America, Asia, and Africa. In the summer of 1976, Eddy participated in a writing conference, designing chemistry 'activities' (problem sets) for Florida State University's Individualized Science Instruction System (ISIS) instruction manual.
Other activities of Eddy in the professional field include service as examiner in chemistry for the independent College Entrance Examination Board and as a consultant to Educational Testing Service, the educational research and assessment organization, where Eddy worked on the Graduate Records Exams and Special Examinations in Elementary Chemistry. Eddy was an active member of the New England Association of Chemistry Teachers (NEACT). He also served as assistant editor to the American Chemical Society's (ACS) publication, Nucleus, and was a member of the ASC's 'Committee of Visiting Scientists,' teaching at the NSF Summer Institutes for Junior High, Senior High, and College teachers at Tufts and at the University of North Dakota.
Eddy married Sarah Elizabeth Frost in 1939. They had two sons and one daughter. He died on January 28, 1983 in Winchester, Massachusetts.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Tested Overhead Projection Series (TOPS); Individualized Science Instruction System (ISIS); Polaris University; WGBH (Television station: Boston, Mass.); New England Association of Chemistry Teachers; American Chemical Society; Faculty papers; Teaching and learning; Eddy Sr., Robert Devereux
- Personal papers, 1935 -- 1982; 1935 -- 1976; MS168.001; 0.55 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists predominantly of biographical material and notebooks dating largely from 1935-1976. It contains resumes, vitaes, notebooks from Eddy's coursework at Brown University and Princeton University, and Eddy's PhD dissertation. Also included are a letter from Eddy to his son, William F. Eddy, and a 'Resolution on the Retirement of Chester Littlefield' to which Eddy contributed.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged first by biographical material followed by chronologically arranged subject files.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - [Biographical, 1 of 3], 1939 -- 1971; MS168.001.001.00001 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [Biographical, 2 of 3], 1942 -- 1980; MS168.001.001.00002 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
    Original folder title: Eddy, Robert D. [from VF]
  - [Biographical, 3 of 3], 1960 -- 1973; MS168.001.001.00003 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
    Original folder title: Biographical - R. D. Eddy
  - [Physics 3 notebook], 1935; MS168.001.001.00004 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [Chemistry 501 physical chemistry notes, binder 1 of 2], 1936; MS168.001.001.00005 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [Chemistry 501 physical chemistry notes, binder 2 of 2], 1936; MS168.001.001.00006 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [PhD Dissertation], 1940; MS168.001.001.00007 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
    Dissertation title: The solubilities of certain inorganic compounds in ordinary water and in deuterium water
  - Chester Littlefield, 1971; MS168.001.001.00008 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [Letter to William F. Eddy], 1982; MS168.001.001.00009 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
- Professional activities, 1942 -- 1976; MS168.002; 0.8 Linear Feet
  This series contains correspondence, publications, manuscripts, television scripts, lectures and course materials generated from Eddy's involvement in professional activities at Tufts and elsewhere, 1959-1976. Included are lectures and writings related to Eddy's involvement in professional associations, including the New England Association of Chemistry Teachers (NEACT) and the American Chemical Society (ACS); also included are chemistry 'activities' (problem sets) designed by Eddy for Florida State University's Individualized Science Instruction System (ISIS) instruction manual (1975-1976), scripts from his WGBH televised chemistry courses for the U.S. Navy's Polaris University (1963), and papers concerning the development of the Tested Overhead Projection Series (TOPS) for classroom use (1965-1975).
  This series is arranged by topic
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
  - [ISIS, 1 of 14], 1974 -- 1976; MS168.002.001.00010 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 2 of 14], 1942 -- 1976; MS168.002.001.00011 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 3 of 14], 1975; MS168.002.001.00012 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 4 of 14], 1976; MS168.002.001.00013 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 5 of 14], 1976; MS168.002.001.00014 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 6 of 14], 1976; MS168.002.001.00015 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 7 of 14], 1975; MS168.002.001.00016 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 8 of 14], 1975; MS168.002.001.00017 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 9 of 14], 1975; MS168.002.001.00018 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 10 of 14], 1975; MS168.002.001.00019 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 11 of 14], 1976; MS168.002.001.00020 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 12 of 14], 1975; MS168.002.001.00021 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 13 of 14], 1975; MS168.002.001.00022 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [ISIS, 14 of 14], 1975; MS168.002.001.00023 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TOPS, 1 of 4], 1965; MS168.002.001.00024 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TOPS, 2 of 4], 1965 -- 1971; MS168.002.001.00025 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TOPS, 3 of 4], 1965 -- 1969; MS168.002.001.00026 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TOPS, 4 of 4], 1965 -- 1976; MS168.002.001.00027 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV, 1 of 2], 1963 -- 1971; MS168.002.001.00028 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
    Original folder title: TV - Dean Phelps, Harvard
  - [TV, 2 of 2], 1971 -- 1972; MS168.002.001.00029 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV slide rule scripts], 1963; MS168.002.001.00030 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV chemistry I scripts, 1 of 2], 1963; MS168.002.001.00031 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV chemistry I scripts, 2 of 2], 1963; MS168.002.001.00032 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV chemistry I and II scripts], 1963; MS168.002.001.00033 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV chemistry II scripts], 1963; MS168.002.001.00034 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV chemistry II and III scripts], 1963; MS168.002.001.00035 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV chemistry III scripts], 1963; MS168.002.001.00036 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV chemistry IV scripts, 1 of 2], 1963; MS168.002.001.00037 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [TV chemistry IV scripts, 2 of 2], 1963; MS168.002.001.00038 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [Course materials, 1 of 4], 1965; MS168.002.001.00039 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [Course materials, 2 of 4], 1965; MS168.002.001.00040 (Box MS168 Shared 1)
  - [Course materials, 3 of 4], 1965; MS168.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - [Course materials, 4 of 4], 1966 -- 1974; MS168.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
    75 years from the date of creation.
  - [High school night address 'on the importance of thinking backward'], 1965; MS168.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - North Dakota trip - summer, 1959; MS168.002.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - PAACT, 1956; MS168.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Publications [1 of 2], 1966 -- 1967; MS168.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Publications [2 of 2], 1967 -- 1969; MS168.002.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Safety manual, 1973; MS168.002.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Salt hydrates, 1962; MS168.002.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - [Untitled manuscript, 1 of 3], 1970; MS168.002.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - [Untitled manuscript, 2 of 3], 1970; MS168.002.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - [Untitled manuscript, 3 of 3], 1970; MS168.002.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - Visiting scientist lecture thru the solar system..., 1962; MS168.002.002.00013 (Box 2)